Finding Aid for United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Lansing Records 1870-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Lansing, Records 1870-1962
United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Lansing (Mich.)
852073 Ba 2
Administrative unit of the Michigan Synod of the United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., established in 1866 and disbanded in 1962, the Lansing Presbytery covered at various times Calhoun, Barry, Eaton, Jackson, Ingham, and Clinton and portions of Shiawassee and Livingston counties. Records include minutes of presbytery meetings and other administrative files.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Lansing Presbytery (Donor No. 769 ), in May 1939. Periodic additions were received
The collection is open for research.
The first Michigan presbytery of the Presbyterian Church was established in 1827. As the territory grew in population so too did the number of churches and thus the need for additional presbyteries to oversee and provide guidance to the individual congregations. In 1833, the Synod of Western Reserve meeting in Detroit worked to resolve the problems and opportunities that the rapidly growing territory of Michigan presented. The Synod determined that the Presbytery of Detroit would now consist of all churches in Wayne County. A new Presbytery of St. Joseph would have responsibility for churches west of the Grand Meridian as well as certain churches in Indiana; and a second new presbytery - the Presbytery of Monroe - would consist of all churches east of the Grand Meridian except for the county of Wayne.
Still further presbyteries were needed for Michigan's western region and mid-section, first with the establishment of the Presbytery of St. Joseph (ca. 1833-34) and later, the Presbytery of Marshall (1838). In 1866, the Synod of Michigan constituted the Presbytery of Lansing to include the counties of Eaton, Ingham and Clinton and the western portions of Shiawassee and Livingston. In the next year or so, the Synod decided to merge the presbytery of Marshall and the newly formed presbytery of Lansing into the Presbytery of Lansing. This new body would consist of churches within the counties of Calhoun, Barry, Eaton, Jackson, Ingham, and Clinton. The Presbytery of Lansing held its first meeting in September 1870.
At the 173rd meeting of the General Assembly of the United Presbyterian Church meeting in May 1961 a resolution was discussed and approved merging and realigning the churches within the Lansing Presbytery effective January 1, 1962. The Presbytery of Lansing was dissolved. In its place, the General Assembly created two new presbyteries: the Presbytery of Grand River and the Presbytery of Southern Michigan.
The record group has been divided into three series:
Minutes of meetings
Administrative Files
Miscellaneous.
The records of the Presbytery of Lansing of the United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. span the 90 year life of the presbytery's existence from its establishment in 1870 through its dissolution and realignment in 1961.
Subjects:
Presbyterian Church--Michigan.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Lansing (Mich.)
- Minutes of meetings
  The Minutes of meetings cover the entire life of the presbytery. The volumes of minutes also include information about the individual churches and pastors of the churches within the presbytery. The minutes are detailed and informative of the activities of the church.
  - 1870-1884 (Box 1)
  - 1885-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905-1908 (Box 1)
  - 1908-1921 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1943 (Box 2)
  - 1943-1955 (Box 2)
  - 1956-1961 (Box 2)
  - General Council meetings 1945-1959 (Box 2)
  - General Council meetings 1959-1960 (Box 2)
- Administrative files
  The Administrative files consist primarily of the files of Stated Clerk Robert Moreland who oversaw the administration of the presbytery in the period up to the time of its dissolution. The dates of most of these files are roughly from 1958 to 1961. Though the record group is devoid of such administrative information for previous decades, these files do provide a glimpse of the activities of the presbytery during the 1950s, especially the workings of the individual departments within the presbytery. Departments especially well documented in this series include Christian Education, Ministerial Relations, and Stewardship and Promotion.
  - Annual reports to the General Assembly and to the Presbytery 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    (include reports from member churches within the Presbytery)
  - Annual meetings working papers 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports/treasurer's statements 1957-1961 (Box 3)
  - General Assembly commissioners 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - List of churches and ministers in presbytery 1960 (Box 3)
  - Ministerial Service 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - Pension information 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Presbyterial Information 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Presbytery Standing Rules 1960 (Box 3)
  - Trustees of the Presbytery General Information and Correspondence 1952-1962 (Box 3)
  - Westminister Foundation (minutes and board reports) 1956-1957 (Box 3)
- Department Files
  The final series - Miscellaneous - includes some historical information and an accumulation of programs special events within the presbytery.
  - Business Affairs
    - Reports 1961 (Box 3)
    - Bills and Overtures 1958-1961 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1960 (Box 3)
    - Session Records 1960 (Box 3)
    - General 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Christian Education
    - General 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Reports and Minutes 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Adult Work 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Camps and Conferences 1961 (Box 3)
    - Social Education and Action 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Youth Work 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Ministerial Relations
    - Reports 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Reports of Ministers 1959 (Box 3)
    - Candidates 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - General 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Mission
    - Reports 1958-1961 (Box 3)
    - General 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Presbytery Causes
    - General 1957-1960 (Box 3)
  - Social Education and Action 1959 (Box 3)
  - Stewardship and Promotion
    - Reports and Minutes 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - First Presbyterian Society of Reading, Michigan, Bethany Chapel 1955-1961 (Box 3)
  - History 1920 and background information, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Programs of church services (ordination, installation, etc.) (Box 3)